Finding Aid for Louis C. Cramton Papers ca. 1865-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Louis C. Cramton Papers
circa 1865-1966
1916-1965
Cramton, Louis C. (Louis Convers), b. 1875.
State Representative from Lapeer, Michigan; U.S. Congressman, 1913-1931, and special attorney to the Secretary of the Interior, 1931-1932; correspondence, speeches, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, campaign materials, and other items relating to his advocacy of the national park system, the concept of historic preservation, fair employment practices legislation, increased support for Howard University and all other aspects of his career.
851130 Aa 2 AC UAm
8 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Louis C. Cramton (donor no. 1677 ) and his son Louis K. Cramton (Donor no. 5121 ). The collection came in multiple accession, 1948-1950 and 1970-1971 and 1987.
The collection is open for research.
Louis Convers Cramton was born in Hadley township, Lapeer County, Michigan, on December 2, 1875. He graduated from the University of Michigan Law Department in 1899, was admitted to the bar, and then began practice in Lapeer at that time. After short stints as a newspaper publisher and secretary to the Michigan Railroad Commission, Cramton embarked on a career of public political service that was both diverse and enduring. He served as a member of the State House of Representatives in 1909 and 1910; was a Republican member of Congress from 1913 to 1931; special attorney to the Secretary of the Interior in 1931 and 1932; circuit judge of Michigan's fortieth circuit court from 1934 through 1941; was elected to the State house of representatives again in 1948 and served until his retirement at the end of 1960. Throughout his public career, Cramton distinguished himself as able legislator, jurist, and lawyer. He was a staunch advocate of the maintenance of the National Park system and of historic preservation of landmarks and buildings. He also championed increased opportunity for the disadvantaged; witness Cramton's legislative efforts to improve the health, education, and industrial development of American Indians, his patronage of Howard University, and his work on the fair employment-practices law in Michigan. Cramton died in Saginaw, Michigan, June 23, 1966.
The Louis C. Cramton papers came to the Bentley Historical Library in three separate accessions (1948-1950; 1971; 1987). The collection has been arranged into six series: Correspondence, Miscellaneous Papers, Topical Files, Newspaper clippings/Scrapbooks, Photographs, and Louis Kay Cramton Papers.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Cramton, Louis C. (Louis Convers), b. 1875.; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926.; Discrimination in employment--United States.; Elections--Michigan--1920.; Elections--Michigan--1940.; United States--Emigration and immigration.; Henry Ford Peace Expedition (1915-1916); Historic buildings--United States.; Howard University.; Immigrants--United States.; Indian Rights Association.; Indians of North America.; Isle Royale National Park (Mich.); Lapeer (Mich.); Michigan. Fair Employment Practices Commission.; Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan--Politics and government--1899-1916.; Michigan--Politics and government--1917-1921.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Navy League of the United States.; People's Lobby.; Presidents--United States--Election--1940.; Public lands--United States.; Republican Party (Mich.); Temperance--United States.; Women--Suffrage--United States.; World War, 1914-1918.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1920.Elections, 1920.; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Dept. of the Interior.; United States. National Park Service.; United States--Politics and government--1901-1953.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Baseball.; Buildings--Michigan--Kingston.; Buildings--Michigan--Lapeer.; Buildings--Michigan--West Branch.; Conservation of natural resources--United States.; Courthouses.; Cramton, Louis C. (Louis Convers), b. 1875.; Hotels and taverns.; Kingston (Mich.)--Buildings.; Knights of Pythias--Michigan--Lapeer.MichiganLapeer.; Lapeer (Mich.); Lapeer (Mich.)--Buildings.; Lumber industry.; Michigan. Legislature.; National parks and reserves.; Offices.; United States. Congress. House.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); West Branch (Mich.)--Buildings.
Contributors:
Albright, Horace M. (Horace Marden), 1890-1987.; American Civic Association.; American Indian Defense Association.; Anti-Saloon League of America.; Burke, Charles Henry, 1861-1944.; Cannon, James, 1864-1944.; Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947.; Cramton, Louis Kay.; Cummins, Albert Baird, 1850-1926.; Emergency Peace Federation (U.S.); Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Hannah, John A., 1902-1991; Hayden, Carl Trumbull, 1877-1972.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Johnson, Hiram, 1866-1945.; Johnson, Mordecai W. (Mordecai Wyatt), 1890-1976; Marsh, Pliny W., 1876-; Mather, Stephen Tyng, 1867-1930.; Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1939.; Mitchell, William, 1879-1936.; Moore, Charles, 1855-1942.; National Security League.; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943.; Pinchot, Amos Richards Eno, 1873-1944.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.; Stone, Irving, 1903-1989; Sullivan, Mark, 1874-1952.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; West, Roy Owen, 1868-1958.; Wheeler, Wayne Bidwell, 1869-1927.; Wilbur, Ray L. (Ray Lyman), 1875-1949.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.; Wirth, Conrad Louis, 1899-1993; Work, Hubert, 1860-1942.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence, 1896-1966
  The Correspondence series is divided into three subseries. The first subseries, dated 1896-1966, also the first to be processed, is heavily weighted toward the period when Cramton was a member of Congress and in the period when he served in the Interior Department, roughly from the mid-1920s to 1933. There is a partial index to correspondents appended to this finding aid for the materials in this first portion of the collection. Cramton corresponded with a wide range of important public figures and notable organizations, such as the American Indian Defense Association, the Anti-Saloon League of America, Hiram Johnson, Mordecai Johnson, Michigan governors Kim Sigler and G. Mennen Williams, U.S. Senator Arthur Vandenberg, and conservationist Gifford Pinchot. This first subseries, though largely correspondence, also includes a scattering of other materials such as memoranda and speeches. The second subseries, though it covers much the same period as the first, 1920-1966, was received following Cramton's death, and includes more personal materials, such as letters of appreciation and letters that Cramton chose not to donate when he was alive. The last subseries consists of letters that Cramton exchanged with members of his family, mainly with his son Louis Kay Cramton, with whom he had a close relationship.
  - Mainly Congressional and Interior Department activities
    - Undated, 1896-1928; 41 folders (Box 1)
    - 1929-1932, 38 folders (Box 2)
    - 1933-1966, 16 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous and personal
    - 1920-1966, 15 folders (Box 3)
  - Family letters (mainly with son Louis Kay Cramton
    - Undated, 1930-1959; 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1960-1966, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Papers, 1893-1966
  Miscellaneous is the arbitrary designation given to groupings of files that Cramton and his son donated to the library. The largest is a chronological run of papers - memoranda, reports, etc. - received by Cramton during the period when he served in the Congress, with the Interior Department, and with the Michigan legislature. This subseries dates from 1893 to 1966. Smaller subseries include bills introduced by Cramton while serving with the state and federal governments, remarks of his from the Congressional Record, campaign materials, genealogical materials, and a collection of the articles, speeches, and other writings made by Cramton during the course of his career.
  - Chronological files
    - Undated, 1893-1930; 26 folders (Box 4)
    - 1931-1966, 16 folders (Box 5)
  - Bills files
    - Introduced in the Michigan Legislature
      - 1909 (Box 5)
      - 1949-1951 (Box 5)
      - 1952-1959 (Box 5)
    - Introduced in the U.S. House of Representative
      - Undated, 1906-1933; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Remarks from Congressional Record
    - 1915-1937, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1950-1966 (Box 5)
      about Cramton or issues in which he was interested
  - Campaign Materials
    - 1908-1916 (Box 5)
    - 1918-1941 (Box 5)
    - 1948-1958 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Tribute to Cramton by the City of Lapeer, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Diary of a trip to Panama and Puerto Rico, undated (Box 5)
    - Travel logs, 1918; 2 volumes in 1 folder bound manuscripts (Box 5)
  - Genealogy
    - General, circa 1930-1960; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Documents, 1747-1918 (Box 6)
    - Families, circa 1900-1960; 23 folders (Box 6)
  - Writings, Articles, Reminiscences, and Speeches, 1897-1962
    - Articles, 1930-1962
      - "The 49'ers in Reorganization,", Undated (Box 6)
      - "The Home Department,", undated (Box 6)
      - "Legislation,", undated (Box 6)
      - "Lunch with the Prince Regent of Serbia and Premier of Greece,", 1938-1962 (Box 6)
      - "When Jeff Davis Reorganized,", 1930-1933 (Box 6)
    - Days of Yore, 1943-1948 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous and Notes, no date (Box 6)
    - Reminiscences, 1960 (Box 6)
    - Speeches, 1897-1966; 2 folders (Box 6)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series was received after Cramton's death, and although similar in content to papers to be found in the Miscellaneous chronological subseries, it has been kept separate. The series reflects his lifelong interests in the National Park system and Howard University.
  - Autobiographical Documents, 1904-1963 (Box 6)
  - Chesapeake Ohio Canal, 1938-1961 (Box 6)
  - Hoover Dam, 1931-1935 (Box 6)
  - Howard University, 1930-1966 (Box 6)
  - Lapeer County Historical Committee, 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Lapeer County Historical Documents, 1850-1878 (Box 6)
    include Lapeer Seminary documents
  - National Parks, 1929-1961 (Box 6)
  - Port Huron Bridge, 1953 (Box 6)
  - Programs, 1892-1965; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Prohibition, 1909-1924 (Box 6)
  - Property and Deeds, 1937-1963 (Box 6)
  - Rotary, 1946-1950 (Box 6)
    include photographs
  - Washington Parkway, 1930-1961 (Box 6)
- Newspaper clippings/Scrapbooks
  The Newspaper clippings/Scrapbooks series consists of clippings about Cramton, arranged chronologically, and two oversized scrapbooks, dated 1910-1912, pertaining to state politics and government.
  - Clippings by date
    - Undated, 1903-1959; 31 folders (Box 7)
    - 1960-1966, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook, 1910-1911 (Volume 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1912 (Volume 2)
- Photographs, circa 1865-1966
  The Photographs series consists of photographs and negatives dated from around 1865 to 1966. The bulk of the photographs depict Cramton in official capacities, but there are also photographs of Lapeer, Michigan which were collected by Cramton. Of special note are the photographs and negatives of Cramton's Western trips; they depict the National Park system in the 1920s and reveal his affection for America's natural splendor.
  - Formal Portraits, 1893-1966 (Box 8)
  - Informal Portraits, 1896-1961 (Box 8)
  - Family, circa 1865-1920 (Box 8)
  - Cramton at Award Ceremonies, circa 1950-1965 (Box 8)
  - Cramton as part of larger group, 1913-1950 (Box 8)
    (also in outsize folder, UAm)
  - Career Photos, 1895-1960
    - Education (Lapeer-UM Law School), 1896-1902 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Railroad Commission, 1907-1908 (Box 8)
    - U.S. Congress, 1919-1930
      - Trip to France, 1919 (Box 8)
      - Western trips, 1920-1929; 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Yosemite visit, 1929 (Box 8)
    - U.S. Department of Interior, 1931-1933 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Legislature, 1948-1960 (Box 8)
  - Collected Photos
    - Chemawa, Oregon, Undated (Box 8)
    - Kingston, Michigan (railroad station), circa 1890 (Box 8)
    - Lapeer Buildings and Organizations, 1883-1910 (Box 8)
    - Lumber camp, circa 1885 (Box 8)
    - West Branch hotel, circa 1885 (Box 8)
  - Album of views of Northern Michigan and Upper Peninsula (Box 8)
  - Unidentified and Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Negatives, circa 1917-1930
    - Cramton Family (Washington, D.C. and camping), circa 1917-1925 (Box 8)
    - Cramton trips West, 1922-1930 (Box 8)
    - Congressional trips, 1918-1925 (Box 8)
    - Numbered Negatives, circa 1921-1929
      detailing Western National Parks
      - 93-163, Yosemite, San Francisco, Fairbanks, Mt. McKinley (Box 8)
      - 164-242, Anchorage, Cordova Glacier, Juneau, Victoria, White Pass (Box 8)
      - 243-327, Mt. Rainier, Yahima Indians, Zion (Box 8)
      - 328-392, North Rim, Glendale, Bryce, Poison Spring, Dirty Devil Rock (Box 8)
      - 397-449, Colorado River, Sun Temple, Mesa Verde (Box 8)
- Louis Kay Cramton (son) Papers, 1951-1967
  The series titled Louis Kay Crampton (son of Louis C. Cramton) consists of a few folders of papers of Louis Kay Cramton mainly, about his father and his father's career. Letters of Louis Kay to Louis C. Cramton are located in the Correspondence series.
  - 1951-1959 (Box 8)
  - 1960-1965 (Box 8)
  - 1966-1967
Selective Index of Correspondents
Albright, Horace M. (Horace Marden), 1890-1987.
1927-1933, June 24, 1958, Nov. 30, 1958, Feb. 6, 1959, Apr. 26, 1960, Aug. 10, 1960, Dec. 2, 1961, Feb. 22, 1962, Nov. 17, 1962, Aug. 15, 1964, June 23, 1966
American Civic Association.
Dec. 18 and 21, 1928, 1930, June 11, 1952, Apr. 9, 1953, June 29, 1955
American Indian Defense Association.
Mar. 30, 1926, Nov. 25, 1927, Dec. 13 and 20, 1927, Feb. 1928, Mar. 24, 1930, Jan. 23, 1931, Feb. 26, 1932
Anti-Saloon League of America.
Dec. 19, 1917, May 21, 1918, June 28, 1918, May 22, 1920, Dec. 15, 1923, Oct. 10, 1924, May 2 and 6, 1925, Oct. 12, 1925, Nov. 8, 1926, Mar. 23, 1927, June 4, 1927, July 6, 12 and 14, 1928, Jan. 28, 1929
Burke, Charles Henry, 1861-1944.
1925, 1926, 1928, 1929, Sept. 23, 1930
Cannon, James, 1864-1944.
1929
Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947.
Jan. 16, 1918
Cummins, Albert Baird, 1850-1926.
1913
Emergency Peace Federation (U.S.)
1917
Green, Fred Warren, 1872-1936.
1927, Feb. 21, 1930, Oct. 13, 1930
Hannah, John Alfred, 1902-
1955, May 17, 1956, Feb. 8, 1960
Hayden, Carl Trumbull, 1877-1972.
Oct. 30 and 31, 1925, Sept. 24, 1930, Mar. 28, 1953
Hoover, Herbert Clark, 1874-1964.
1929, Feb. 1, 1935
Indian Rights Association.
Mar. 20, 1926, Jan. 11, 1929, May 13, 1930, Jan. 27, 1931
Johnson, Hiram Warren, 1866-1945.
1920, Nov. 21, 1923, Dec. 15, 1923, Mar. 31, 1924, Aug. 8 and 9, 1930
Johnson, Mordecai Wyatt, 1890-
undated, Jan. 16, 1930, Oct. 9 and 17, 1930, May 11 and 26, 1931, Feb. 25, 1932, Feb. 17, 1954, May 31, 1955, July 1, 1955, Aug. 29, 1955, Feb. 21, 1958, Apr. 26, 1960, June 30, 1960, Nov. 25, 1960, Apr. 11, 1962, July 25, 1964, May 2, 14 and 20, 1965
Marsh, Pliny W., 1876-
Mar. 31, 1911, Apr. 7, 1911, July 7, 1919, 1924, May 26, 1949, 1951, Jan. 2, 1952, Apr. 16, 1960
Mather, Stephen Tyng, 1867-1930.
undated, July 8, 1925, Oct. 5, 1925, 1927-1929
Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1939.
May 15, 1924, Jan. 3, 1925, Feb. 6, 1925, Mar. 27, 1929, Apr. 17, 1929
Mitchell, William, 1879-1936.
Nov. 27, 1920, Dec. 1, 1920, Jan. 1925
Moore, Charles, 1855-1942.
1929, Sept. 19, 1930
National Security League.
Oct. 2, 1915, Mar. 16 and 18, 1916
Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943.
1930, Jan. 19 and 27, 1931
Pinchot, Amos Richards Eno, 1873-1944.
Feb. 13 and 15, 1917
Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946
Aug. 8 and 9, 1928, June 6, 1940
Sigler, Kim, b. 1894.
June 7, 1945, Mar. 7, 1946, Apr. 19, 1946, June 28, 1946, Sept. 23, 1948, Mar. 23, 1949, Oct. 21, 1949, Jan. 22, 1951, Feb. 11, 1951, May 14, 1951
Stone, Irving, 1903-
Sept. 11, 1944, Oct. 6, 1944
Sullivan, Mark, 1874-1952.
May 19 and 20, 1920
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Mar. 23, 1920, Apr. 3, 1930, Dec. 4 and 6, 1930, 1931, Nov. 27, 1937, May 31, 1939, June 15 and 18, 1940, July 8, 1940, Jan. 23 and 26, 1943
West, Roy Owen, 1868-1958.
1928, 1929, Sept. 21, 1930
Wheeler, Wayne Bidwell, 1869-1927.
June 28, 1918, May 22, 1920, Oct. 10, 1924, May 2 and 6, 1925, Oct. 12, 1925, Nov. 8, 1926, Mar. 23, 1927, June 4, 1927
Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1875-1949.
1929-1933, July 20, 1935
Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-
undated, June 8, 1949, Apr. 21, 1954, Nov. 6, 1954, June 16, 1955, Nov. 11, 1958, Apr. 19, 1960, Dec. 31, 1960
Wirth, Conrad Louis, 1899-
Dec. 19, 1951, Oct- 13, 1954, July 9, 1956, 1957, Feb. 5, 1958, June 24, 1958, Dec. 2, 1959, May 16, 1960, Nov 21, 1962
Work, Hubert, 1860-1942.
1924, 1925, 1927, 1928
Selective Subject Index
Debs, Eugene Victor, 1855-1926
See letter to Irving Stone, September 11, 1944
Henry Ford Peace Expedition (1915-1916)
See letter dated December 1, 1915
Indians of North America
See correspondence with American Indian Defense Association and the Indian Rights Association, especially during the 1920s and 1930s
Isle Royale National Park
See correspondence, Feb. 1930 and Feb. 1931
Navy League of the United States
See correspondence, 1915-1916
People's Lobby
See letters of Feb. and April 1930
Temperance
See correspondence with the Anti-Saloon League of America and with Wayne B. Wheeler.